<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE oim SYSTEM "oimxml.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY nbsp  "&#160;">
  <!ENTITY lsquo "&#8216;">
  <!ENTITY rsquo "&#8217;">
  <!ENTITY minus "&#8211;">
  <!ENTITY times "&#xd7;">
  <!ENTITY copy "&#xa9;">
  <!ENTITY eacute "&#233;">
] >
<oim xmlns:dk="http://www.kirsanov.com">
<partopen dk:number="IV" id="Appendices">
<title>Appendices</title></partopen>

<chapter id="Appendix-A">
<chapopen><title>Making a Good Cup of&nbsp;Tea</title>

<epigraph dk:padding-top="48">
<p><line>I'm not a connoisseur.</line>
<line>I actually drink the stuff.</line></p>
<attribution>Me</attribution>
</epigraph>
</chapopen>

<h1>Basics of Making Tea</h1><h1s>

<p><idx start="a_tea">tea</idx>Most of the world knows how to make tea, but there is at least one
major industrialized nation in which the preparation of a decent cup
of tea is a lost art.  These are very basic guidelines for the
uninitiated, covering black tea <dk:nobr>in particular.</dk:nobr></p>

<ul>
<li><p>Use loose tea; avoid teabags.  Your best bet is to find a good tea
shop with knowledgeable staff.  If you live in the US, you may have to
look online.</p></li>

<li><p>Use a good teapot.  A mostly-spherical ceramic pot is a good
place to start.  Make sure that the lid won't fall out when you pour.</p></li>

<li><p>Warm the teapot by filling it with hot water.</p></li>

<li><p>Bring fresh aerated water to a full boil.  Just before it
reaches boiling, empty your teapot and put in the tea.</p></li>

<li><p>As soon as the water boils, pour it into the teapot.  Cover the
teapot with a towel or tea cozy.</p></li>

<li><p>Let the pot sit quietly for about four minutes.</p></li>

<li><p>Pour the tea from the pot through a strainer into your cup.</p></li>
</ul>

<p>You will want to experiment with this a few times to find out how
much tea to use, whether or not you like milk in your tea, and how
much sugar (if any) you like.  If you use milk, add it to the cup
before you pour the tea.  For a typical American mug, use
approximately one glorp of milk, which is just a bit more than a full
slosh.  A glorp should more than cover the bottom of the mug and turn
the tea a pleasant, warming, light brown color.</p>

<p><b>Never</b> use cream in tea.  Use whole milk, preferably at room
temperature.  The term "Cream Tea" refers to tea served with
scones,<idx>scones</idx> jam, and whipped (or, preferably, Devonshire
Clotted) cream.  The cream and jam go onto the scones, not into the
tea.</p>

<p>When putting tea into the teapot, forget everything you ever
learned about coffee.  The rule of thumb for tea is "one teaspoonful
of tea for every cup plus one for the pot."  Note, however, that the
name "teaspoon" really does have meaning.  If you use too much tea,
the result will be heavy and bitter.  Too little tea and you will have
what Jonathan Swift described as "water bewitched."</p>

<email>
<pre>From: Matthew Geddes<idx>Geddes, Matthew</idx>, Xavier College, South Australia
  To: tng-technical@lists.dcerpc.org

I was just reading Appendix A and thought it might be worth 
mentioning that tea should only be drunk from white cups. For some
reason, it don't taste right out of coffee cups (well, non-white 
ones anyway). And china also appears to make the tea taste better.
</pre>
</email>

</h1s><h1>About Tea</h1><h1s>

<p>A neighbor of mine lived in India for a while, and told me that he
had once toured a tea packing plant. He said that the best tea was
sold to places like Australia, Russia, and the
Middle East which have long had access to the very best quality tea.
The middle quality tea was either kept for local consumption, or sold
to Western Europe.  The bottom quality tea was sent to the United
States.  This means that Americans need to do some looking if they
want to find good tea.</p>

<p>Tea can be green, Oolong,<idx>Oolong</idx> or black, depending upon
the degree of fermentation.  A green tea is unfermented and will have
the least caffeine,<idx>caffeine</idx> Oolong tea is partially
fermented, and black tea is fully fermented.</p>

<p>The terms Assam,<idx>Assam</idx> Ceylon,<idx>Ceylon</idx>
Darjeeling,<idx>Darjeeling</idx> and Yunnan<idx>Yunnan</idx> all refer
to the region in which the tea is grown. Each has its own
characteristics.  There are also special words describing which leaf
of the tea shoot was picked and how the leaves were processed.  Earl
Grey tea is actually a blended black tea with a special flavoring
added, and note that the term "Orange Pekoe" refers to the size of the
processed tea leaves, not the variety of tea.  A box labeled Orange
Pekoe is typically a box of unspecified tea, probably packed into
teabags.</p>

<email>
<pre>From: Olaf Barthel<idx>Barthel, Olaf</idx>
  To: Chris Hertel

...Incidentally, "pekoe" reportedly is chinese for "white down" and
refers to the young tender tea leaves. It doesn't have to be bad 
tea, although it's often hard to tell what the heck "orange pekoe" 
is supposed to be.</pre>
</email>

<p>Tea is not really tea unless it is made from the leaves of a
specific plant, <i>Camellia sinensis</i>.<idx>Camellia sinensis</idx>
There are several products called "herbal tea" that are not tea at
all, but fall instead into the category of "herbal infusion."</p>

</h1s><h1>Nasty Habits</h1><h1s>

<p>The teabags sold in UK supermarkets tend to make stronger tea than
their rather frightening American counterparts.  If you can get hold
of some British teabags, you can make tea the way they do at London
train stations.  We call this British Rail tea.</p>

<p>When you order a cup of tea at a London train station they dump
milk, sugar, teabag, and boiling water into the cup at the same time
and then hand it to you.  This makes for a uniquely generic flavor
that is just right for an early morning zombie
commute.  You can achieve similar results on a larger scale by using a
full-sized insulated carafe instead of a cup.  This should last you
all morning, and keep you "going" all afternoon.<fn>Caffeine is a
diuretic. Tea generally has less caffeine<idx>caffeine</idx> than
coffee, but if you drink an entire carafe's worth of either over the
course of a morning you will need to visit the facilities.</fn></p>

</h1s><h1>Decaffeinating Tea</h1><h1s>

<p>You can decaffeinate tea at home by following these steps:</p>

<ul>

<li><p>Add a little extra tea to the pot.  (This process will rob a
little flavor from the tea.  Adding more tea helps compensate.)</p></li>

<li><p>When the water boils, pour it on and wait about twenty to
thirty seconds.</p></li>

<li><p>Pour the water out through a strainer, returning any captured
leaves to the pot.</p></li>

<li><p>Pour on freshly boiled water, and steep as usual.</p></li>
</ul>

<p>This process will remove about eighty percent of the caffeine,<idx>caffeine</idx>
which dissolves very quickly in water.</p>

<p dk:padding-top="12pt"><em>Author's note:</em> I am not British.  I live in
Minnesota where hot drinks are required for winter survival.  I did
live in the UK for a year, many years ago.  Being a foreigner I had to
"try harder" in order to fit in - so I learned.  Several years later
someone accused me of being a "tea expert."  I am no such thing.  In
fact, I know very little about tea.  Unfortunately, the tiny amount of
knowledge I do have seems to be more than most American restaurant and
caf&eacute; employees can claim on the subject.<idx
end="a_tea">tea</idx></p>

</h1s>
</chapter>
</oim>