<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE oim SYSTEM "oimxml.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY nbsp  "&#160;">
  <!ENTITY lsquo "&#8216;">
  <!ENTITY rsquo "&#8217;">
  <!ENTITY minus "&#8211;">
  <!ENTITY mdash "&#8212;">
  <!ENTITY times "&#xd7;">
  <!ENTITY copy "&#xa9;">
] >
<oim xmlns:dk="http://www.kirsanov.com">
<chapter id="SMB2.11">
<chapopen><title>That Just about Wraps Things Up for SMB</title>

<epigraph dk:padding-top="36">
<p>
<line>Let's just get rid of these</line>
<line>horrible protocols.</line>
</p>
<attribution><line>Andrew Tridgell,<idx>Tridge</idx></line>
<line>Samba Team Leader </line></attribution>
</epigraph>

</chapopen>

<p>If the Internet has proven anything, it's that a very large number
of primates<idx>primates</idx> banging randomly on keyboards over a
long enough period of time can and will produce some amazingly useful
software.  On the other hand, if you gather some of those primates
together, place them into cubicles, and train them to perform like
circus animals...
</p>

<p>...well, we've just put a lot of effort into cleaning up the mess
that was made in those cubicles. A shame, really. It was a nice little
protocol when it started out.</p>

<p>Although the SNIA<idx>SNIA</idx> gave it their best shot, there are
currently no industry committees or standards groups writing <em>bona
fide</em> specifications to be reviewed and voted on, and no standard
test suites to verify conformity. That's not to say that
specifications and test suites don't exist - quite the contrary. The
problem is that they have no teeth. With no real standards and no real
enforcement, the only measure of correctness for an SMB implementation
is whether or not it works <em>most</em> of the time.  Since
<em>most</em> of the clients out there are Windows clients, the
formula simplifies down to whether or not an implementation works with
Windows. An additional problem is that SMB itself is not enough for
true interoperability with Windows systems - particularly if you want
to write a workable server.</p>

<p>In San Jose, California, there is a mansion known as the Winchester
Mystery House. It started out as a simple farmhouse, but it was
expanded over a period of thirty-eight years by a millionaire widow
with an obsessive compulsion to keep on adding new rooms. It has
stairways that rise directly into the ceiling, windows in the floor,
doors that open to solid walls... and that's just for starters. The
building covers four and a half acres and has an estimated 160&nbsp;rooms.</p>

<p>CIFS is like that.</p>

<p>The original SMB protocol was simple and well suited to its
environment. Over the years, however, it has been greatly expanded.
Several sub-protocols have been added on as well. These subprotocols
(which include the Extended Security protocols, RAP<idx>RAP</idx>,
MS-RPC<idx>MS-RPC</idx>, etc.) are implemented by Windows - so, if you
want to build something truly compatible, SMB alone just isn't
enough.</p>

<p>...but don't go away feeling that it is all just a hopeless
mess. It is really a question of how much effort you are willing to
put into solving the problems you will encounter. Take it one step
at a time, because the individual pieces are much less daunting
than the whole.</p>

</chapter>
</oim>