<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE oim SYSTEM "oimxml.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY nbsp  "&#160;">
  <!ENTITY lsquo "&#8216;">
  <!ENTITY rsquo "&#8217;">
  <!ENTITY minus "&#8211;">
  <!ENTITY mdash "&#8212;">
  <!ENTITY times "&#xd7;">
  <!ENTITY copy "&#xa9;">
] >
<oim xmlns:dk="http://www.kirsanov.com">
<chapter id="Browsing3.6">
<chapopen><title>Samba Browse Service Enhancements</title>
<epigraph dk:padding-top="48">
<p>
<line>If you want something done right</line>
<line>you have to do it yourself.</line>
</p>
<attribution>Well-known axiom</attribution>
</epigraph>
</chapopen>

<p>Sit back and think about it for a minute... There are a lot of ways
to fiddle with the Browse Service. That could be good, or it could be
bad. (Now would be a good time to check your firewall
configuration.)</p>

<p>Samba<idx start="c24-samba">Samba</idx> takes advantage of the fiddlability of the
Browse Protocol to improve the workings of the Network
Neighborhood.<idx>Network Neighborhood</idx> It may break a few rules,
but it gets the job done... sort of like Chicago.<fn>Don't argue. I
used to live there.</fn></p>

<p>Samba's Browse Service<idx>Browse Service</idx> enhancements are
worth a bit of study, because knowing how to gracefully break the
rules can provide a better insight on the proper workings of the
system. </p>

<h1 id="Browsing3.6.1">Automatic LANMAN</h1><h1s>

<p>There may still be systems out there that run the old LAN Manager
style browsing. Things like that don't die, they fade away... but,
just when you think they've finally faded entirely they reach a
skeletal hand up through the damp earth and grab your ankle. It's best
to be prepared for such events, and Samba offers a very simple clove
of garlic.</p>

<p>Samba's <code>smb.conf</code> configuration file provides the
<code>LM ANNOUNCE</code><idx>LM ANNOUNCE</idx> parameter, which is
used to enable or disable the transmission of LAN Manager Browse
Service announcements. This parameter has three possible values:
<code>TRUE</code>, <code>FALSE</code>, or <code>AUTO</code>. The third
option is the interesting one.</p>

<p>In <code>LM ANNOUNCE = AUTO</code> mode, Samba will not send any
LAN Manager-style announcements until (and unless) it hears a LAN
Manager Browse Service message from another system. If it hears such a
message, it knows that LAN Manager style browsing is being used on the
local wire and will start participating. This mode is the default for
Samba, and it means that System Administrators don't ever need to
think about configuring LAN Manager style browsing. It's automagical!
</p>

</h1s><h1 id="Browsing3.6.2">UnBrowsable</h1><h1s>

<p>The <code>BROWSABLE</code> parameter can be used to completely hide
a share. Share names ending with a dollar sign (&lsquo;$&rsquo;) are
supposed to be hidden, but it is up to the client to decide whether or
not to display these names. They are included in the reply to the
<code>NetShareEnum</code><idx>NetShareEnum</idx> RAP<idx>RAP</idx>
call, so the client can do as it pleases with them.</p>

<p>Samba can be told not to include a share in the
<code>NetShareEnum</code> reply message simply by setting
<code>BROWSABLE&#160;=&#160;NO</code> in the share declaration. This
moves control to the server side and allows a System Administrator to
really truly hide a share. </p>

</h1s><h1 id="Browsing3.6.3">NBNS Wildcard DMB Queries and Enhanced Browsing</h1><h1s>

<p><idx start="c24-dmb">DMB</idx>Samba's implementation of the
NBNS<idx>NBNS</idx> supports a non-standard wildcard Domain Master
Browser query<idx>wildcard<sidx>Domain Master Browser query</sidx></idx>. You
can send a query for the name "<code>*&lt;1B&gt;</code>" (that's an
asterisk, followed by 14 bytes of <em>either</em> space or nul
padding, with a suffix byte<idx>suffix byte</idx> value of
<code>0x1B</code>), and Samba's NBNS will return a list of all of the
IP addresses of all Domain Master Browsers that have registered with
it. In other words, all of the IP addresses for all of the
<code>&lt;1B&gt;</code> names in its database.</p>

<p>If the <code>ENHANCED BROWSING</code> parameter is set to
<code>TRUE</code> (the default), a Samba DMB will periodically send a
query for "<code>*&lt;1B&gt;</code>" to the NBNS to get the list of
DMB IPs. The Samba DMB will then go through the list of IPs and send a
<code>NODE STATUS REQUEST</code> message to any IP address that it
doesn't already recognize. The reply will contain the registered
<em>workgroup</em><code>&lt;1B&gt;</code><idx
type="1B">workgroup</idx> name of the "foreign" DMB.</p>

<p>This trick is used by Samba to short-cut the building of the
workgroup<idx>Workgroup</idx> list. The normal mechanism relies on Local Master
Browsers<idx start="c24-lmb">LMB</idx> to discover foreign workgroups
on their own subnet and report them back to the DMB. That process is
slow and, as shown in <ref refid="Figure3.10"/>, workgroups can be
isolated on separate subnets where they will never see or be seen by
foreigners. By querying the NBNS for the list of DMBs, Samba does a
better job of ensuring that all of the workgroups within the NBT
namespace<idx>NBT<sidx>namespace</sidx></idx> know about one
another.</p>

<fig id="Figure3.10">
<img dk:width="340" loc="BRO10"/>
<caption>Hidden workgroups</caption>
<subcaption><p>The <code>ARTHROPODS</code> and <code>MAMMALS</code>
workgroups are isolated because there is no subnet on which they both
have a Local or Domain Master Browser. Workgroups normally find one
another by broadcasting <code>DomainAnnouncement</code> messages on
the local LAN. Samba can query the NBNS to find Domain Master Browsers
on remote subnets, and synchronize with them to merge isolated Browse
Lists.<idx>Browse List</idx></p></subcaption>
</fig>

<p>...but it's not perfect. There might be workgroups out there
that don't have a DMB, in which case querying the NBNS for DMB
names won't help much. With Enhanced Browsing enabled, a Samba DMB
will try to find lost workgroups by periodically querying other
DMBs to see if they know about them. The Samba DMB then adds any
missing workgroups to its internal list.</p>

<p>There is a downside to this second trick, which is that bogus or
expired workgroup names, once added to the Browse List, may never
disappear. Samba DMBs may wind up sending the bogus names back and
forth like an urban legend. This is known as the "Dead Workgroup"
problem. The comments under <code>ENHANCED BROWSING</code> in the
<code>smb.conf</code> manual page suggest disabling this feature if
empty workgroups won't go away.</p>

<p>Note that Windows also has a work-around for this problem. You can
specify foreign DMBs in the <code>LMHOSTS</code><idx>LMHOSTS</idx>
file on a known DMB, and the DMB will include the foreign names in its
Browse List and try to synchronize <dk:nobr>with them.</dk:nobr> </p>

</h1s><h1 id="Browsing3.6.4">Remote Announce</h1><h1s>

<p>The Remote Announce feature allows a Samba server to announce
itself to Local and Domain Master Browsers anywhere across the
internetwork. The format of the <code>REMOTE ANNOUNCE</code> parameter
is:</p>

<pre>remote announce = [<em>IP</em>[/<em>workgroup</em>]{"&#160;"<em>IP</em>[/<em>workgroup</em>]}]</pre>

<p>That is, a list of zero or more entries, separated by spaces, in
which each entry consists of an IP address and an optional
workgroup<idx>Workgroup</idx> name. The IP <dk:nobr>and
workgroup</dk:nobr> are separated by a slash. The Samba server will
send <code><dk:nobr>HostAnnouncement</dk:nobr> Browser
Frames</code><idx>HostAnnouncement</idx> to the specified IP address
(which could be either a host or a broadcast address). If the
workgroup name is specified, the Samba server will announce itself as
a member of that workgroup, otherwise it will use the name specified
by the <code>smb.conf WORKGROUP</code>
<dk:nobr>parameter.</dk:nobr></p>

<p>As a result of using this feature...</p>

<ul>
<li><p>An isolated server can send a directed broadcast to a subnet,
where an LMB might pick it up.</p></li>

<li><p>An isolated server can announce itself directly to the
DMB.</p></li>

<li><p>A single server can show up as a member of many
workgroups.</p></li>
</ul>

<p>Be careful, though, a misconfiguration can really mess things
up. </p>

</h1s><h1 id="Browsing3.6.5">Remote Browse Sync</h1><h1s>

<p>Samba servers running as Local Master Browsers can be configured to
synchronize with one another directly, without the need for a DMB. The
notes in the <code>smb.conf</code> manual page explain that this is
done in a Samba-specific way. The trick is fairly simple,
though. Samba unicasts a <code>MasterAnnouncement Browser
Frame</code><idx>MasterAnnouncement</idx> to the remote IP
address.</p>

<p>You may recall that <code>MasterAnnouncement</code> messages are
supposed to be sent to DMBs. An LMB sends them to let the DMB know
that the LMB exists. The DMB then sends a
<code>NetServerEnum2</code><idx>NetServerEnum2</idx> request to the
LMB to collect the Browse List<idx>Browse List</idx> and merge it with
the master list... but you knew that.</p>

<p>Samba's extension is that a Samba LMB will also respond to a
<dk:nobr><code>MasterAnnouncement</code></dk:nobr> message and synchronize with the
sender.</p>

<p>It is suggested, in the <code>smb.conf</code> docs, that the
destination addresses be specified as subnet broadcast addresses.
Current network best practices recommend against allowing directed
broadcasts, however, so on most networks you won't be able to send a
broadcast message to a remote subnet. To really make this feature
work, you will need to know the IP address of the Local Master Browser
on the remote subnet. One way to do this is to ensure that a specific
Samba server on that remote LAN always wins the LMB
election.<idx>election</idx><idx end="c24-lmb">LMB</idx></p>

<p>You can fiddle the <code>PREFERRED MASTER</code> and <code>OS
LEVEL</code> parameters in such a way that Samba will always win the election.
</p>

</h1s><h1 id="Browsing3.6.6">DMB != PDC</h1><h1s>

<p>A Windows system cannot offer DMB services unless it is also the
PDC.<idx>PDC</idx></p>

<p>Samba can.</p>

<p>Note that it doesn't work the other way 'round. If Samba is
configured to be a PDC then, like Windows, it must also be the DMB
for the NT Domain it serves.<idx
end="c24-dmb">DMB</idx><idx end="c24-samba">Samba</idx></p>

</h1s>
</chapter>
</oim>