<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE oim SYSTEM "oimxml.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY nbsp  "&#160;">
  <!ENTITY lsquo "&#8216;">
  <!ENTITY rsquo "&#8217;">
  <!ENTITY minus "&#8211;">
  <!ENTITY mdash "&#8212;">
  <!ENTITY times "&#xd7;">
  <!ENTITY copy "&#xa9;">
] >
<oim xmlns:dk="http://www.kirsanov.com">
<chapter id="Browsing3.7">
<chapopen><title>It Can&#8217;t Happen Here</title>
<epigraph>
<p><line>Debugging browsing</line>
<line>problems is difficult</line>
<line>to say the least...</line></p>
<attribution><line>Benjamin Carter<idx>Carter, Benjamin</idx></line>
<line>in an e'mail message</line>
<line>to the Samba-Technical</line>
<line>mailing list</line></attribution>
</epigraph>
</chapopen>

<p>Trouble in the Network Neighborhood? What could possibly happen
to disrupt the peace and prosperity of such a stable, well run, and
deliberately <dk:nobr>happy place?</dk:nobr></p>

<p>Well, any society that puts presentation ahead of principle is
bound to suffer. The Network Neighborhood<idx>Network
Neighborhood</idx> is far from being an exception. Many things, most
of them trivial, can throw a monkey-wrench into the works. To its
credit, the Browse Service is fairly resilient and recovers quickly
once the problem has been rectified. It also helps that it's a
non-critical system. Still, fixing the problems generally requires
intervention by a qualified expert. Unfortunatly, there aren't many of
those around so trained professionals wind up with the job, poor
dears. Let's see what we can do to help them... </p>

<h1 id="Browsing3.7.1">Misconfigured Hosts</h1><h1s>

<p><idx start="c25-dmb">DMB</idx>One of the most common and obvious
problems, once you know what to look for, is a misconfigured
host. Things that can go wrong include:</p>

<dl>
<dt>The wrong workgroup<idx>Workgroup</idx> name in the
configuration</dt>

<dd><p>Perhaps you entered "<code>WROKGROPE</code>" when you meant to type
in "<code>WEIMARANER</code>".</p></dd>

<dt>Browser services disabled</dt>

<dd><p>There are Windows restistry settings and Samba<idx
start="c25-samba">Samba</idx> configuration settings that can prevent
a node from becomming a Potential Browser.<idx>Potential Browser</idx>
If there are no browser nodes on the LAN, then the Network
Neighborhood<idx>Network Neighborhood</idx> will fade away like
Brigadoon.</p></dd>

<dt>Browser services over-enabled</dt>

<dd><p>A node with its OS level or other criteria set too high can win
elections<idx>election</idx> over a node that is a better
choice.</p></dd>

<dt>A misconfigured or missing NBNS<idx>NBNS</idx> server address</dt>

<dd><p>Local browsing will work fine without an NBNS, but cross-subnet
browsing will fail. Proper NBNS (WINS<idx>WINS</idx>) configuration is
required for cross-subnet browsing.</p></dd>

<dt>P mode</dt>

<dd><p>In P mode, the Consumer<idx>Browse
Service<sidx>Consumer</sidx></idx> <em>must</em> deal directly with
the Domain Master Browser. That only works if there is a
DMB, and the NBNS is configured correctly. In many
cases, the Consumer node should really be running in H or M
mode.<idx>P</idx><idx>H</idx><idx>M</idx></p></dd>

<dt>User not authenticated</dt>

<dd><p>Some client systems require that the user be logged on before
they start SMB services. Also, some Browse Servers require
authentication<idx>authentication</idx> before they permit access to
the <code>NetServerEnum2</code><idx>NetServerEnum2</idx>
call.</p></dd>

<dt>Prolific protocol bindings</dt>

<dd><p>This is the biggie. </p>

<p>In the old IBM/Sytec<idx>Sytec</idx> days<idx>IBM</idx> there were
these things called LANAs<idx>LANA</idx> (<b>LAN</b>
<b>A</b>dapters). We would call them NICs (<b>N</b>etwork
<b>I</b>nterface <b>C</b>ards) today. The original
NetBIOS<idx>NetBIOS</idx> software spoke directly to the LANAs so,
logically, when you build an emulated NetBIOS LAN you also have
virtual LANAs.<idx>NBT<sidx>vLAN</sidx></idx></p>

<p>On some systems, such as Windows, you can "bind" the NetBIOS layer
to several different protocols. We have focused on NetBIOS over
TCP/UDP/IP, but Windows can also bind NetBIOS to
NetBEUI<idx>NetBEUI</idx> and to something called NWLink (which is
Microsoft's<idx>Microsoft</idx> implementation of Novell's
IPX/SPX). Each binding represents another virtual LANA.  That means
that a Windows system with NetBIOS bound to multiple transport
protocols is a multi-homed<idx>multi-homed host</idx> host, as shown in
<ref refid="Figure3.11"/>.</p>

<fig id="Figure3.11">
<img dk:width="220" loc="BRO11"/> 
<caption>Multiple virtual networks</caption>
<subcaption><p>A node with NetBIOS bound to two transport protocols is
logically connected to two separate virtual NetBIOS LANs.</p>

<p>Consider what happens when node <code>STEFFOND</code> wins the
Browser Election on the IP LAN, after which node <code>CONRAD</code>
calls for an election on the NetBEUI<idx>NetBEUI</idx> LAN and
wins. The two nodes are not on the same (virtual) LAN, so they do not
know that they are competing.</p></subcaption>
</fig>

<p>One potential result of this configuration is an election storm, in
which the <code>RequestElection</code><idx>RequestElection</idx>
frames keep getting sent out (via both virtual LANAs, in some cases)
but there is never any clear winner, so the elections have to start
all over again. The Leach/Naik Browser draft addresses this issue by
warning that a broswer node <em>must</em> be aware of the separate
virtual LANs to which it is connected.<fn>Do election storms really
happen? I have heard reports of them, but never seen one
<dk:nobr>first-hand.</dk:nobr></fn></p></dd>
</dl>

</h1s><h1 id="Browsing3.7.2">Misconfigured Networks</h1><h1s>

<p><idx>node type</idx>Network configuration errors can also upset the teacart.</p>

<dl>
<dt>No DMB</dt>

<dd><p>If there's no Domain Master Browser, then cross-subnet browsing
won't work (<em>unless</em> you set up Samba's extensions
correctly).</p></dd>

<dt>Separated namespaces</dt>

<dd><p>Namespace manglement is a big deal in the CIFS world, in part
because it is so easy to mess it up. The NBT
namespace<idx>NBT<sidx>namespace</sidx></idx> can be fractured if
multiple, unsychronized NBNS servers are used or if P, B, and M/H
nodes are mixed in the same
environment.<idx>B</idx><idx>P</idx><idx>M</idx><idx>H</idx></p>

<p>The Browse Service relies heavily on the NBT Name
Service<idx>NBT<sidx>Name Service</sidx></idx>, so it is important to
make sure that the NBT namespace is consistent.  Otherwise, the
Browsers, Providers,<idx>Browse Service<sidx>Provider</sidx></idx> and
Consumers<idx>Browse Service<sidx>Consumer</sidx></idx> won't be able
to find <dk:nobr>one another.</dk:nobr></p></dd>

<dt>Isolated workgroups<idx>Workgroup</idx></dt>

<dd><p><ref refid="Figure3.10"/> showed what this problem looks
like. Unless workgroups are physically mixed on the same LAN, the
LMBs<idx start="c25-lmb">LMB</idx> won't find one another and won't
exchange <code>DomainAnnouncement</code><idx>DomainAnnouncement</idx>
frames. That means that the workgroups will remain isolated.</p></dd>
</dl>

</h1s><h1 id="Browsing3.7.3">Implementation Bugs</h1><h1s>

<p>This is unverified,<fn>...mostly because I don't have enough
equipment to really test it.</fn> but reliable sources report that
Windows 9x systems running as Local Master Browsers do not bother to
synchronize properly with the Domain Master Browser. If true, it would
cause a bit of a problem with cross-subnet browsing. The common
solution is to grab an old, outdated PC and load an Open Source OS on
it. Then install Samba and configure it to <dk:nobr>win elections.<idx>election</idx></dk:nobr> </p>

</h1s><h1 id="Browsing3.7.4">Troublemakers</h1><h1s>

<p>Back several years, there was a bug in a release of Samba
(somewhere in the 1.9.16 series) that would cause a Samba server to
register the <code>&lt;1B&gt;</code> DMB name instead of the
<code>&lt;1D&gt;</code> when it won a local
election<idx>election</idx> and became an LMB.  This bug caused all
sorts of trouble, particularly with regard to the Primary Domain
Conroller<idx>PDC</idx> which, due to the rules of NetBIOS
naming,<idx>NetBIOS<sidx>name</sidx></idx> was unable to
<dk:nobr>register itself.</dk:nobr><idx end="c25-dmb">DMB</idx><idx
end="c25-lmb">LMB</idx><idx end="c25-samba">Samba</idx></p>

</h1s><h1 id="Browsing3.7.5">Design Flaws</h1><h1s>

<p>Now that you know how it works, you can decide for yourself. </p>

</h1s>
</chapter>
</oim>