<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE oim SYSTEM "oimxml.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY nbsp  "&#160;">
  <!ENTITY lsquo "&#8216;">
  <!ENTITY rsquo "&#8217;">
  <!ENTITY minus "&#8211;">
  <!ENTITY mdash "&#8212;">
  <!ENTITY times "&#xd7;">
  <!ENTITY copy "&#xa9;">
] >
<oim xmlns:dk="http://www.kirsanov.com">

<foreword>

<epigraph dk:padding-top="92">
<p></p>
</epigraph>

<p dk:indent="no">Writing a book is hard - writing a <em>good</em> book is very hard,
and describing an area as complex as CIFS is a nightmare.  The biggest
pleasure of being involved with the production of this reference is in
the clarity and depth of the end result - the impossible has been
achieved, for the benefit of all involved in this protocol.</p>

<p>CIFS is an important protocol - indeed, in Windows networks it
could be considered as important as TCP/IP, as almost all
communication between Windows machines can flow over it.  It provides
file and print services, and, among other things, is a carrier for
Remote Procedure Call and NT Domain services. When I came to CIFS in
2001, it was out of an interest in the Samba project - an Open Source
implementation that I was running on Linux - where I soon became a
specialist in Authentication.  At the time, there was little good
documentation available, particularly on the murky details of
<dk:nobr>authentication.</dk:nobr></p>

<p>For that reason, you will find my name scattered all over the
Authentication area of this book. As a developer of a CIFS
implementation, there are many things that I now know - and needed to
know then - that were never clearly written down.  Too often, the only
reference on some functionality was the C code that implemented it -
and the implicit hope that comments vaguely represented reality.  I
personally spent many hours inspecting the publicly available sources
of Samba and Samba-TNG, in the hope of gleaning some extra
understanding, some critical detail.</p>

<p>My role in this book was one of many willing victims - exposing all
I knew about CIFS, realising how little we had all actually proved,
and how much we just assumed.  Chris' role was that of interrogator -
asking all the difficult questions, and forcing us all to re-evaluate.
The end result was a lot of testing, experimentation, and analysis, but
also the solid research foundation behind this massive effort.</p>

<p>My hope is that with this book, future developers will no longer be
required to pore over cryptic standards drafts - or badly commented C
code - to understand the "big picture" into which their software
sits.</p>

<p>More remarkably however, <cite>Implementing CIFS</cite> provides a solid
technical reference on the protocol as a whole - between the
standardese of the SNIA Technical Reference included as an appendix
and the clear English of Chris' own chapters is a wealth of technical
information that aids even the most experienced developer.</p>

<p>Beyond that, by creating such readable documentation, Implementing
CIFS allows more than blind faith in vendors words - CIFS is now
assessable to network administrators and other non-programmers who
can understand for themselves how this protocol works (and how it
doesn't).</p>

<p>By leading readers though the creation of his own basic CIFS
client, Chris Hertel ensures that readers have a solid background in
the basics - and can continue on to implementing the rest of the protocol
sure of their foundations.</p>

<p>I've very much enjoyed working with Chris Hertel on <cite>Implementing
CIFS</cite>&nbsp;&mdash; finally, I could see a description of this protocol that mere
mortals could not only understand, but also enjoy!</p>

<author>Andrew Bartlett<idx>Bartlett, Andrew</idx></author>
<description>Samba Team</description>
<place>Canberra, Australia</place>
<date>June 2003</date>

</foreword>
</oim>
